howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
unfortunately we had some technical
issues while recording this episode and
the sound quality isn't up to our
usual standards nonetheless it's very
listenable and the content
is great
today's guest is kamal sinclair cabal is
the executive director of the guild of
future architects
and she also works supporting
independent artists as a senior
consultant for sundance institute's
future
of culture initiative and she makes
art through a family practice that she
calls sinclair futures
she also serves as an external advisor
to the macarthur foundation's journalism
and media program
and is a member of mit's center for
advanced virtuality
i read this somewhere i don't know if
you said it or someone said it about you
but anyway i found the words you could
say that come off sinclair is an
art duel now six months ago i wouldn't
have known what a doula was
but it turns out i'm a brand new grandpa
for the first time
how about that right congratulations
thank you i
may be biased but in my opinion most
beautiful baby in the world
but anyway hula is a new thing at least
since
we were in the child making europe and
our daughter had one and
she was very very helpful as a process
essentially a very experienced advisor
on the whole pregnancy process and
advocate when you need it
that's what a doula is at least in the
pregnancy business
and so that gives me a quite interesting
sense of you
as an art doula
thank you yes it's something that has
emerged as a term i would say
from a lot of practice of helping
artists to birth their creative babies
over 20 years
hopefully in general there's less blood
and bodily fluids
but i'm sure well
you'd be surprised we did uh support
when i was at sundance um
heather dewey hagborg who is a
bioengineering artist
so she definitely got into some of the
uh human um
you know tissues and so forth in her
birthing of her her creative vision
pretty cool i also call out that cabal
has a very interesting tweet stream that
kamal sinclair and man is it nerdy i
mean some deep let me tell
you i read two of the most recent ones
one that's basically a
quite detailed and reasonably accurate
article on the metaphysics of star trek
style
transporters is the person on the other
side really you
read the article and find out another
article is
on is consciousness quantum phenomenon
again a deep question and the author
comes to the correct answer which is
maybe and the third one which is blew my
mind is the mathematics of
earth bending and you know i'm a pretty
mathematical dude but by about
a third of the way in i said ah this
shit's over my head but anyway
check out her amazing tweet stream if
you're prepared
to go deep continuing a little bit with
her long bio which i had to edit down
she's done amazing amount of cool stuff
previously she served as a director of
sundance institute's new frontier labs
program for seven years which supports
artists working at the convergence of
film art
media and technology we're gonna talk
about all those things and how they come
together
earlier in her career she was a trans
media producer
42 entertainment and worked on projects
as the legends of alcatraz for jj
abrams mark of the spider-man and random
acts of
fusion very interesting people listen to
the show regularly know
my good friend jeff gomez starlight
runner has also been on the show
episode 23 where he and i talked about
narrative and cultural
change he's another guy who calls
himself a trans media producer
and this is an area that i am very
interested in
okay great um thank you so much jim for
such a
kind uh generous uh time to
to go through through my bio i always
tell people they're like have you done
so many eclectic things i'm like
it's kind of failing forward is how i
talk about how i ended up in so many
different spaces
um but certainly thrilled to have
had these experiences in these
intersections of art science technology
and the work of you know designing
better futures
and better systems for those futures the
reference that you made to my
my super nerdy tweet stream i have to
say i
have been around a lot of nerds in my
life and i'm a proud nerd myself for
sure
but i think my son who is the author of
those blog posts
beats me on the nerd on the nerd scale
quite
quite high because he's um 18 but been
kind of deeply entrenched in i would say
like a physics philosopher i i think all
physicists are philosophers
but um he's deeply engaged in the kind
of philosophy that physics
you know asks of us about you know our
reality so
hey guys that's that shocks the hell out
of me that he's 18. because the stuff
read like
someone with a phd tell you the truth
wow that's a great
great um great to hear because he's
applying for college for next year so
hopefully
the admissions teams will feel the same
way but
yeah he's um he's yeah very very special
young man
and teaches me things every day and we
we have these deep conversations around
things like you know the things that are
breaking
for me in terms of my awareness of how
science and technology
are breaking the kind of barriers
between
what we assumed was magic you know the
things that we identified as magic or
sci-fi
when they start to become real through
the advancements in our understanding of
science and the advancements of
the wielding of science for
technological advancement
you start to ask these really
philosophical questions around
whoa how is this breaking my previous
sense of what
was real and what was magic and so we
talk a lot about
that kind of ever-changing line between
between those two and how the arts
particularly have a kind of liminal
relationship with with both in the way
that they can
break with science in order to imagine
the fantastical but then in some ways
open up our minds to go
huh i wonder if we should explore that
um
and see if there is some some scientific
or technological
truth behind this event it's what seems
like just pure imagination
so it's yeah fun times around the dinner
table
that sounds really good now one through
line that i saw on a lot of your work
at least since when you stopped being a
performer we may get back to you about
the performer's side but maybe
not is story and the evolution of
storytelling as you say in the liminal
space between that
you know the deep history of
storytelling which probably goes back to
the dawn of language
and today where we're at this
intersection
of our typical narrative plus so many
different
media it's unbelievable so at the
highest level
what do you see as where we're at in the
evolution of storytelling maybe a little
history of
storytelling as you perceive it yeah
and i i definitely want to say that i've
been influenced i have a lot obviously
we all have a lot of influences but
particularly on this subject i would say
alex mcdowell from the world building
institute has
we've had a lot of great conversations
about it and i definitely have learned
from him how he's framed this particular
evolution of storytelling but i think
what i have
observed is that we have these moments
where
you know storytelling from the early
earliest times
has allowed us to communicate
our emotions our ideas it's it's it's
part of what makes us
human it's part of what makes us able to
to operate as you know
on an abstract level that kind of
distinguishes us in some ways
i want to be careful about this it
distinguishes us from
other living beings but in some ways we
are
deeply in gratitude or need to be deeply
in gratitude to other
systems of you know life that educate us
through
like you know i think of octavia butler
and how she would observe
she was an amateur scientist she was a
sci-fi writer amateur scientist she
would
observe things like slime mold in her
her little home lab and identify how
these systems of organic systems would
actually
be something that could educate humans
about how to better design our own
societies and systems so i was about to
say that it distinguishes from us from
the animals or from the plants but in
some ways
our storytelling allows us to better
access what is already an inherent
lesson in those
other living structures so when you
think about you know there's so much
research around storytelling in the
brain and
the nature of language in the brain and
i think that that is
fascinating i remember hearing an npr
piece and i wish i had the exact
reference but i don't
where there was some children that had
pretty much had the
kind of raised themselves alone in
um a part of the jungle in south america
and were found at like eight nine ten
years old
um how this happened don't know but
there was an interview with one of the
children who now was a grown person
and they talked about how they had a an
instinctual relationship to life and
reality
it was very about you know food shelter
sleep like the very fundamentals of
survival and when they
became and met and grew and started
integrating with other people and
developed language for the first time as
a 10 year old or eight-year-old
they actually started having abstract
thought
on a higher level and and that is really
interesting
so you think about some of the ways in
which intelligence even works
is that it works through storytelling we
create through language and through the
sharing
of information back and forth between
people and trying to describe our
lived experiences to each other that's
how we access
deeper and higher and more abstract
levels of intelligence
so going back that far to story that's
like the fundamentals
but what's also interesting is that as
science and technology evolve we have
these disruptions
to our sense of reality right we learn
that that the
earth is not flat we learn that the sun
doesn't revolve around the earth
and these things fundamentally break
what we thought was our
fundamental reality and that is
the scientists and and the technologists
that are enabling observation or these
mathematical
observations or so forth that is one
critical point in disrupting our reality
but then the next
step is that the philosophers and the
artists and the storytellers
have to recalibrate our sense of what
does that mean
how does that make meaning how does that
how do we recalibrate the meaning of our
existence
and i think that's where story is
critical because
it's through those stories that are told
that we help
each other recalibrate we allow
ourselves to design systems
you know kind of help prescribe and
um adopt behaviors and so
we've seen this over pattern over and
over and over again and
in the last you know you look at 500
years ago the printing press coming
around
it completely changed people's sense of
reality people could read things like
the bible for themselves for the first
time literacy started to jump and so
forth
then you have things like television
coming into play
right around where things like vietnam
you're able to see the front lines in
real time
and it changed people's relationship to
war in a lot of ways
when you think about seeing earth from
space people
change their sense of borders and
nations with that massive
communication and that story that
narrative that was being shared globally
and now we are at another disruption
of our sense of reality and that is
things like the bioengineering
advancements artificial intelligence and
advancements
and the nature of communication
architecture in general
is totally disrupting our sense of
reality especially for those that have
at the kind of forefront of these fields
and it is critical that i in my opinion
that artists people from humanities
philosophers
are in conversation in collaboration
with the scientists and technologists
to help us to contextualize what does
this mean for our reality you have
people like yuval harari that are
claiming this is the beginning of
homo dias and the end of homo sapien
okay that's a bold
narrative to begin how do we create a
collective conversation
and dialogue about that is that
something that we want to evolve into is
that really true
like these are this is how story is
critical for us trying to contextualize
our reality well very very well said
right
of course these challenges of new
information technologies go way back
those of us remember our socrates
remember that
old socrates had a pretty good view of
writing he thought oh damn
it changes for the worse if we lost our
oral tradition and the ability to recite
the iliad from memory and what do you
think now
we came back in some social media holy
moly
right yeah i mean i mean my kids have
all the time this conversation around
cursive writing
they have no idea like
why do you guys like they can do their
signature and that's about it and they
don't
understand the utility of cursive
writing but it's it's really interesting
to have some people
advocate strongly for maintaining that
even though
functionally it's not necessary anymore
that kind of quick writing that
cursive i mean my understanding is that
it was invented to because you're
having to when you we were in a
pre-printing press
kind of communication architecture
cursive writing allows you to go faster
smoother
um you know it just it sped up the
process and it was a gorgeous art form
but is that a utility we need anymore is
there something between the hand
eye brain neurological relationships
that are we losing something
and i think that's what is really
interesting about the conversations
that are happening at the guild of
future architects where i am currently
um you know kind of the key area of my
focus right now
is that we're constantly negotiating
between
what you know what of our past
have we lost that was something that we
needed to maintain
because now in hindsight we can see how
that would have benefited us to
to maintain like certain practices or
marginalized
ideas and then other things that you
know what is it that we're willing to
let go of and how do we let go of or
does it move into something
that is an archived version of it rather
than a functional part of it
these are very challenging issues and
i'll i'll say
one example that lynette walworth who's
an artist that we work with talks about
a lot
is how um indig a lot of indigenous
practices around the
world maintained kind of practices that
would have been
disregarded in a scientific revolution
kind of environment
as shamanistic kind of
superstition right and now there's
scientific evidence emerging
that some of these practices have
especially around
understanding intuition and uh i guess
the senses she was saying that we always
understood sight smell like these very
basic senses as
the human input for data and now they're
starting to discover that humans
actually have many more
layers of senses that are input for data
such as
that would be similar to understanding
weather patterns understanding
things like how fish know when to go up
the stream and spawn
like we have other kind of senses and
relationships to our ecosystems that
we've dulled in western or in
modern societies that have in many
indigenous practices that are modern
societies and i want to be clear about
that i'm not
that those things can were maintained
and and they've been dulled another so
that's an example of like
what did we lose assuming that
our current sense of what is true could
only be
understood through sight sound smell
hearing
touch that we dulled things that were
less explicit but just as empirically
um important in terms of data input for
our sense of reality
so this is a hard it's like how and so i
think it requires
a real constant gardening of
conversation dialogue and
open-mindedness to
explore all of that absolutely and you
know there's
as you say there's a lot of scientific
touch points
for instance there's a whole school of
cognitive science
that holds that maybe our main cognitive
skill that makes us different than
chimps is telling stories
i recently had nick chaderon who goes
further than anybody
he has a radical book called the mind is
flat
and he he basically says all that idea
of depth in your head
it's wrong it's basically just a bunch
of perceptual memories plus the ability
to make up stories on the fly
and that's all you are he may go a
bridge too far but it is very
interesting and he quotes
lots and lots of real cognitive science
and real
neuroscience research and michael
gazzaniga with his split brain work
also highlights what he calls the
explainer function of the left brain
and that you know especially in the west
where we're very left brain oriented
you know we identify ourselves with
these explanations that our brain makes
up
even when it's getting bad data because
the brain has been split
in fact i call it the confabulator just
make up right
to my mind one of the first steps
towards art was the first person that
realized you could use
language for life right that's a word
[Laughter]
well it is interesting that i mean i
grew up
my father would always say to us the
reality of a human being is their
thought
right so i think therefore i am so
there's a lot of these ideas around
and when you think about if the reality
of a person is their thought
then and you think about um i had a
conversation with a billionaire
a couple years ago um who was
a really wonderful you know entrepreneur
who had
done an incredible job of building out
um
a venture capital fund around medical um
innovations but what was interesting is
he had no idea
when kind of all of the kind of binary
left-right
uh racial tension stuff started coming
up
um post around the 2016 election cycle
he was shocked he really had
thought that all of the racial tension
in this country had been resolved in the
civil rights movement
and that everything was hunky-dory and
so he was shocked and so it
he was surprised that he could be such a
powerful um
person in the world and you know he's
and and be this ignorant
of the people that live just you know
down the
down the road from him or in the same
town um having very different
experiences of the american experience
and to me that and so he went to this
like very this like two-year
deep dive into all these things and he
was like wow
he said my world has been quite
filtered for me to only experience a
version of america
and for it to be so filtered from what
my neighbor or
someone else living in the other part of
town is experiencing he said he was just
shocked at how
you can have two totally different
realities living in the same town
and i think that that's what your like
that mind is flat
kind of notion to me like that's what i
hear is
you know even though there's so many
layers to reality you can walk around
and see from a pedestrian point of view
you know
the things that human beings perceive
and completely miss
the tardigrades
like that perspective and that's a
reality that's a that's a filter bubble
right
and so so we do i think and that goes to
ideological realities it goes to i mean
all of those things like what is
our reality is i mean we are and stories
are what illuminate those different
levels of our even understanding or
perception of how we can understand
those things
and you can make up and we live in
a false reality as well
and we know some people that do these
days
and of course the arts are really
important for bridging
that gap right because it is easy to
live within a filter bubble but if you
pursue deep art you will find more of
the truth than if you don't
for instance i grew up working class
half a redneck
fairly regressive attitudes about race
all kinds of bad things
and for me one of the biggest bridges
was my high school
english teacher said you should really
read james baldwin you will really like
him
because i had a love of language i had a
love of deep thinking i had a love of
sort of radical you know heart on your
sleeve writing and she said don't read
james baldwin so i did and kept reading
and reading and reading
and it radically changed me as a human
being
to understand that the doctrines i'd
heard
from my neighbors and you know most of
high school dropouts and what have you
wasn't really the whole story and so i
went through a big portal
through art and baldwin is a great
artist let there be no mistake about
that
he's an artist before he's a polemicist
though he is also both
but the quality of his writing it just
stirs you just reading it
oh yes he is definitely one of my
inspirations and
and aspirations in life is
definitely baldwin and others um of his
generation
and just to your point like it also is
really interesting to think about
well first of all i just want to you
know also honor
you being very vulnerable to say hey i
had this perspective and i've learned
and shifted
same i i want to be equally vulnerable i
mean i grew up
at a time when when it comes to race i
would say i grew up in a pretty
enlightened environment but
when it comes to lgbtq identities it was
very unenlightened
and went through a similar kind of
awakening of
my own bias and ignorances uh
and and it's just kind of like really
surprising
to me to be the same human being that
had a completely different understanding
of reality then than i do now
so it is interesting how we evolve in
our thinking through story
through relationships you know they call
out a new
voice who i think is hugely powerful and
has made a big impact on me and some
people
tyson yunka porta he is a australian
aboriginal
fellow as he would call himself written
a book called
sand talk which does something very
cheeky which is essentially he's doing
reverse anthropology looking back out of
the world with a lens
of two things simultaneously aboriginal
indigenous culture and complexity
science
at the same time it's mind-boggling
that's tyson young
porta san talk if you want something
that can change your perspective
in a pretty major way this fairly thin
book will do it and
like james baldwin it's also a great
work of art
not just intellectually interesting
highly call him out he's appeared on my
podcast three times that's how
strongly i love his work you know you
mentioned it let's jump into this
which is question bridge when i was
doing my research for this podcast
i dug into question bridge in fact i'll
confess to having spent four hours
cruising around it and this is a thing
questionbridge.com check it out this is
again
one highly useful to help you think and
change how you think i mean how i'm an
old white dude
you know am i totally up to speed on
what actual real-life black men of all
sorts you're thinking
no and so spending four hours i wish i
had 20 hours
because it's really cool
thank you and it's also by the way
beautifully produced i mean i've done a
little bit of movie production what have
you and the cinematography is first
class the lighting is astounding
the staging is very very simple but very
appropriate etc
let's dig into question bridge a little
bit and you know tell us where the idea
came from
and sort of the mechanics how it worked
where the questions come from
how did you connect the questioners and
the answers which seem
must have been voluntary and
self-organizing something like that the
way it worked oh definitely
yeah so thank you so much for for
spending that amount of time on the
platform and uh with
with these incredible um voices so
question bridge is a media facilitated
dialogue among black men in america
and it started actually in 1996 by chris
johnson
who's one of the collaborators on the
question bridge black males version
but he did a version in 1996 between
um african americans in san diego that
were
wealthy or in the upper class and those
that were
in a lower income bracket trying to
bridge the gap
in terms of these incomes and what was
the influence for him is
he was in brooklyn when redlining ended
and the fair housing
act happened and he saw he would say
within months
the flight of high-income black folks
from black communities
and that was the beginning of he said
within a month he would see
the doctor's office boarded up the law
offices boarded up
certain stores started getting boarded
up and you
basically had gone from a very mixed
incoming kind of healthy
ecosystem even though it was oppressed
from the
larger ecosystem of economics it at
least within
the microcosm of the black community
there was a diversity of
folks and that ended and then you saw
the beginning of
the kind of quintessential black
american ghetto
and he was really interested in trying
to understand that dynamic so that was
where it started in 96
and some incredible insights came out of
that well hank willis thomas one of our
other collaborators was a
student of his in grad school and saw
him present on this work that he had
done
and he approached him and said can we
update it but instead of looking at
this economic conversation can we really
just have a dialogue among black
men in america and so that led to
you know a 10-year project and the
basic methodology is put a camera in
front of
a black man a person identifies as black
and male and say
can you ask a question of another black
man that you feel distant or estranged
from
and so we would capture these questions
on camera and sometimes they were very
specific questions like
you know i want to ask this of any black
police officers or i want to ask this
of you know black men that are dating
white women or of gay black men
or sometimes they were just general any
person that identified this way
and then we would go meet with other you
know
put calls out on facebook all kinds of
different ways
to set up a opportunity for people to
respond to those questions and then ask
their own questions so it was a very
emergent project and by the time i got
involved
they had a thousand question and answer
exchanges
and um i remember the first night uh
they were
showing me these clips and me and dr joy
de gru
who wrote the book post-traumatic slave
syndrome we were both together and they
were asking for our advice
and we were looking through this and we
were like you can't edit out any of
these voices and put it into a
documentary or even into
an installation in a museum because as
soon as you edit out
any one of these voices it becomes your
perspective on black male identity
rather than the organic reality of black
male identity
and so that's where we decide where i
had been working in
early exploration research on trans
media and interactive media
very influenced by artists like kat
sizzik who
was pioneering interactive participatory
documentary at the time
and that's where the idea of bringing it
to an interactive
place where you did not ever have to cap
who got to
bring their voice to the conversation
and it turned into
a lot of different forms and has been
now um archived at the smithsonian
african-american museum very cool like
terminals there you go
and play with it on or how was it
archived yeah so we basically we had a
five-channel installation
that was a three-hour edit of all these
voices and then we would have laptops um
or
tablets um kiosks where people could
explore the
according to their own curiosity the
full unencumbered
um kind of uh grouping of voices i mean
basically i think what you you saw on
questionbridge.com
um and they could also add if they if
they self-identified as black and male
they could contribute
their own question and they can answer
any questions so
it became and not only was it about the
video dialogue
but we also asked them to create a
fingerprint profile
trying to reappropriate you know what
normally is used to
kind of especially in the mass
incarceration system kind of book
black men into a very limited identity
as criminal or thug or violent
um and kind of unlock that fingerprint
to show we ask them to tag themselves
with as many different identity tags
as they felt authentically described
them and we had a hypothesis that
it would probably break the container of
this thing called black and male because
it would be
so many different tags that it you could
never say
black men are dot dot dot and in any
kind of certainty
because the and and i think our
hypothesis was proven
we created a word cloud and it was very
few words
that um ended up being used over and
over and over again
people found so many different ways to
identify themselves in so many nuanced
ways
that it shows the true complexity then
we also had people
tag their dialogue and also allowed for
like a wikipedia-style tagging of the
dialogue
and that also that data visualization
was also incredibly complex and diverse
so
it really kind of shows the diversity of
thought and the diversity of identity
within this
kind of container yeah very cool and by
the way those tags were searchable
as i was doing my play i saw it had a
search box i started searching and i
realized i was getting things
that weren't in the words themselves so
i said ah
must be some tagging going on here
yeah yeah and it produced some very
interesting navigations
to give people a sense i'm gonna if you
don't mind call out some of the
questions
that were asked and in some cases give a
little sense of some of the answers
is that okay by you i would love it
thank you
yeah one that happened to be the first
one i pulled up and there seems to be a
certain amount of randomness of what you
see next
was very from the heart was how do we
learn to love a woman when we didn't
have a good role model at home
and many of the guys struggled with it
and were sad
and confused but they were engaged with
it it was
moving you know holy right
one of them was particularly funny in a
way though not
you know serial funny i'd call it was do
you have a problem
eating chicken watermelon or a banana in
front of white people
yeah and some people said yes i do
others said no i don't
but i think one of the best and funniest
was a guy
you know he came on pretending to be
really serious
he looked like a bourgeois business dude
right he said
my family has been in the wholesale
watermelon business since 1933.
now in a month indiana in chicago
so eat watermelon all the time right
i go i love it right absolutely
that was a deep question it was so funny
it was one of our
kind of most played you know kind of
question answer exchanges
and yet it's so many so much depth in
the answers
as well as humor so i'm glad you pointed
that one out
it was a good one i mean again there was
some serious discussion this was rich
all this stuff was rich and how you got
these people to be so engaged at this
level of
richness there was some real good
something something going on there
another one maybe the deepest one i saw
was how does it feel to see someone lose
their life
yeah and it was a quite a mixture of
people on that one you know from
corner guys to conservative bourgeois
religious guys a homicide
cop how about that a soldier and just
plain working guys
all reflecting on that and i go oh dear
man this is some
rich and deep stuff and we didn't
prescribe any of it
it all just came from that one question
of ask a guy something that
you you know you feel some ask someone a
question that you feel distance and
estranged from and
isn't that amazing when you just keep a
simple
request to ask that simple question it
unlocks
this much depth and yeah in terms of
setting the tone
it was yeah i can well basically it was
interesting to see
the way my collaborators would i would
not be in the room when they were
filming because um it kind of changed
the environment when
i as a woman um was in the room it
it there was a little bit of a different
relationship and when i was out of the
room it was really just black men
in the room talking to other black men
there was a
vulnerability that was just phenomenal
and i feel so honored that we got a
chance that they shared themselves in
this vulnerable way on film so that we
could all
engage with their humanity that is just
mind-blowingly beautiful yeah just
screamed
authenticity to me i said damn there is
no here
that's true it was really good i made
notes on about ten of them but i'm gonna
go with just one more
and this is back to your earlier point
and the question was
does being black mean i have to be one
thing that fits
in a box and you know i thought it was
very healthy that nobody
thought that right yes yes but they saw
it in very different ways and they
acknowledged the fact that maybe the
world saw him in a box sometimes right
and i thought it was one of the richer
discussions and again
you know something that's very very good
just on that point
we created a 9 through 12 grade
curriculum and
we would do teacher trainings um with
with teachers and
i was doing a teacher training in
brooklyn uh and they were all black
teachers in the room um and and i played
that
that question on video i said you know
what is it um
basically what are the parameters of
blackness you know uh
what makes you black and then i went
around the room and i said
what do you do that is not black
and so the whole group had things that
they do
that are considered not black some of
them were
going hiking some of them were knitting
one of them was i'm a member of the
polar bear the polar bear club in new
york city
you know folks that jump into the into
the hudson
in the middle of winter and um and then
you know i
until we then we had this deep
discussion like wow so being black means
you can't see a sunrise or a sunset on
top of a mountain
being black means you can't knit being
black means you can't
you know have this adrenaline rushed
experience like it's so interesting
that how everyone broke it but everyone
had subscribed to
this idea of the limitations of
blackness that they were
they broke almost in like a oops i ain't
acting black now but
really it's kind of really telling the
kind of ways in which we tell ourselves
stories that put us in our own
boxes and other people also perform
this kind of limitation yeah anyway
sorry go ahead
yeah yeah no no very very important and
good you know
frankly my advice to everybody is if you
think you're in a box blow the damn box
up
exactly yeah it's not good for you it's
not good for the world and someone tries
to put you in a box
tell them to go themselves
[Laughter]
now one thought that struck me and again
this is questionbridge.com people go
look at particularly if you're an old
white dude like me you'll learn
something
is have you thought about applying that
technique to other domains i mean the
obvious one would be black women
absolutely um so that's the reason it
was question bridge
calling black men because we actually
had intended to do not just black women
but we were creating a
question bridge platform that people
could start their own question bridges
based on their
identity group they wanted to start and
build out and so we
unfortunately the money that we were
raising for it didn't come in
and so we couldn't further it but we may
revisit it again
maybe we'll get some investor that might
come back around
yeah let me know i'll promote it i know
some rich people okay
sounds good i would pay money to see
the same technique applied to black
women if i got as much out of it as i
got out of the black men one i would go
hell yes this is a very very important
work of art
wow thank you so much jim all right well
let's move on now to a little
more technical space which is vr virtual
reality is an area you've worked in and
thought about quite a lot in fact a
very tightly enumerated google search
produced 5400 hits for come on sinclair
and vr
virtual reality whoa
that i did not know that that's crazy
i do nerdy stuff like that sometimes
why not the tools are there right
what do you see as how vr can enhance
the power of storytelling
oh wow so you know i just have to say
i have to give a lot of credit to shari
frilo who's the founder of new frontier
at sundance and the chief curator
um i came on board pre-vr
when we were looking at a lot of
interactive documentary gaming filming
inter intersections and
and things that were computational art
but i was virtual reality was
you know something that people tried in
the you know 90s or
you know and it never really took off
right and then
shari um saw this piece by noni de la
pena
called hunger in los angeles at usc
um and was just really struck by this
you know this kind of attempt to
extend journalism so that it wasn't just
like we know television and film
extended journalism
by giving people a visual even a more
kind of
sense of liveness of the visuals of
what's happening right now
and uh noni's goal was to put you inside
and be complicit in the pieces that she
was reporting on
which is kind of gives you an even more
kind of complicit relationship with our
with our news so she decided to bring
this to sundance in 2012
and we couldn't bring the headset from
usc to park
city um it was a 50 000 headset they're
like heck no
and so her intern at the time was palmer
lucky who created the oculus rift
and he said oh i can maybe
use a smartphone um and uh figure out a
head
mount to allow people to still see this
through
to that smartphone and so that became
the prototype for the oculus rift and
that came to sundance in 2012.
so i've gotten i say all that to say
that having been there
that year and i've gotten this kind of
really front row seat
to watching the kind of this wave of
innovation around virtual reality
and then augmented reality as well as
all kinds of
mixed reality hyper reality uh kind of
take off and i've seen a lot
and sometimes when i present on the
works that have been quite influential
most people i i was at brown university
a couple years ago
and after i did this big presentation on
all the different ways that i had seen
virtual reality being
invaded on and experimented somebody
raised their hand and said i'm starting
to think that virtual reality is a
oral storytelling tradition because
i never get to see any of these things
and
i'm dying to see them but the
accessibility was so limited right
i was probably one of the few people
that had because i got flown around the
world
all the time to see people at the
cutting edge be able to experience this
so i say all that to say that most
people that have experienced virtual
reality have seen something that i would
say
is far inferior to the work at the
kind of heightened levels of the medium
and i think it's just it's really
unfortunate because there's so much
incredible work happening in this medium
that has
never even been experienced so i say
that to start us
off um but i would say that some of the
aspects of
it's it's more than just going into 360
environment
and seeing you know the front back side
up and down
of an environment the things that are
being innovated in the space are
being able to for example
one national theater in the uk did a
piece
where it was one actor that was in full
mocap
connected to one audience member who was
also in
mocap and also uh had a virtual reality
headset on
and it was a story of a young man
saying goodbye to his mother who's dying
of cancer and so the whole virtual
experience
was hand-drawn illustration and very
very effective and so you're as a
audience member you're in this
hand-drawn illustration
of the story um having the last moments
with your mother
and because there's a one-to-one
relationship and the actor is
in mocap in real time whenever the
character in the film
grabs your hand the actress also grabs
your hand so you're feeling
the touch of a human touch while seeing
this other reality through your
visual input and it is
she tucks you into bed she gives you a
hug and the experience
of having that level of a hyper reality
experience of the story
makes you feel like you're really there
on a level that you don't get from
um seeing things from a flat screen
from a distance you could certainly see
the potential
but yet at least in the mass audience
somehow it's
fallen way short of our expectations
hugely
why do you think that is i mean you
would think that this is a natural
extension of say computer gaming
or something and yet you know it's funny
i'll confess to having been a gamer for
the last
55 years right wow
that yes you are definitely the expert
over
my experience and i go back to you know
war games like the avalon hill games
little cardboard pieces on a cardboard
map
and do every iteration of gaming from
the early apple
all the way up to you know powerful
stuff that only runs on a 2 000
computer but and this is the interesting
thing i was thinking about this
but i have never looked at a vr
game and the answer is because i've
never gotten enough social proof
from somebody else that it's worth my
while to do so
well i would tell you my experience and
it could be a wrong analysis but
from being on the ground of the not only
the diy
makers but also the early kind of folks
that were had some resources to do
really incredible investment like the
early days of
oculus story studios and the work that
they were doing with sasha unseld
as a creative director stuff was amazing
but what was the ch this literally i was
told
by a number of investors both
venture capitalists as well as those
coming from certain gaming and filming
kind of executive
backgrounds that people got burned
during the free
content times of when you know the the
cd
and the dvd started to fall and you
didn't have a tangible
transaction for revenue to come into a
company and everything was kind of
loose on the internet and people really
got burned in terms of their investment
into content
and so when when virtual reality and
this 1500
headset came on to the scene in terms of
investment people got
really excited about oh we can invest in
this hardware
and we can see a revenue threshold that
we haven't had
since the dvd that we haven't had since
the cd
and um and that
was a big carrot on a stick for industry
and for investment
but when it came to investing in content
the thing that we heard over and over
and over again was oh
the content community the maker
community will figure that out we're not
going to invest in that
because everyone got burned and i
actually did a series of interviews with
people
uh within the industry i interviewed 130
people and this i heard this over and
over and over again
and so the only artists that were
getting funded with any serious money
were people that had a
patentable technology or some ip
that was not content i.p but it was
patented
or patentable hardware or software
and it wasn't the content itself so we
felt
so by the time you know the big hope was
when playstation came out with their
headset everybody was like oh good this
is going to be the great hope for the
industry
and we were a billion dollars short in
revenue expectations for that christmas
and the reason over and over that was
stated was there was no content
why you can spend 1500 or even 900 on a
headset
with no content and i think that that
was a huge
quite frankly because i did see
incredible content
but it was so little snippets nobody
really invested in the right way
so i think that's one of the analyses
there could be many others
that people might come up with um the
other thing to be quite
frank the most compelling xr experiences
that i've had
are installation based and they're not
something that you can put into a home
um and that's not the best business
model for people that are looking for
the new dvd
indeed yeah yeah when you're talking
about the you know the ip rip
offs and yeah that's certainly been a
big issue in certain media but as you
pointed out
once you got the playstation you now
have a grounded medium
for making money right because they
knock that damn thing down pretty hard
right
and if you want the content you got to
pay for it so you would have thought
that if there was a space for
reasonably accessible exploration say
for a few million dollars
people would have tried it and yet i
guess they did but
as i said i've got no social proof no
friend of mine has come to me and said
jim god damn it you have to check this
out
right and so you know my sense is that
somehow it has failed
even though it now has a platform for
which real revenue could be made
i mean we know how big the game market
is it's huge right
it's huge and i think another challenge
was
i definitely that was said over and over
again like all the content makers that
we
were supporting couldn't we're having
the hardest time in the world getting
the support that they needed because
it's expensive it's expensive to
prototype and to
to really fine i mean the sitcom didn't
come until 20 years after tv
was established as an emerging medium
right so
you know where are we on that curve
we're you know i mean
vr is a 40-year medium but with this
particular jump in the fidelity and
the ability to have higher quality
work um the other thing i often cite is
when people first started trying to put
content on a blackberry that was
shitty experience it was horrible and so
i don't think
and then you know come 20 2016 i
remember i
binge watched game of thrones on my cell
phone
maybe like 80 hours because i couldn't
watch it on my tv because i had little
kids in the house
so you know in my own within a 10-year
period i went from
i'm not even gonna watch a short video
on this
thing called a smartphone to i'm binge
watching 80 hours
on a smartphone and so i just you know
want to also kind of
look at that and i don't know if the vr
headset as it is currently designed
is that end unit like a television set
or
an apple phone of the ultimate
experience for
xr experiences i think we're still on
that
learning curve but i can tell you the
people that the things that i've seen
that have blown my mind
and compelled me both emotionally in
terms of
you know entertainment and in terms of
just pure
artistic enthrallment those artists were
not getting money
to support their work i can say that
without a doubt
is there anything that you would
recommend that say that's available on
either a pc or a playstation that
is worth having social proof that it's
worth the effort to take a look at
i would say all the things that i have
seen that i love
are not available on those platforms all
right we'll leave it at that
okay that said something people right it
does
we're not there yet here's one of the
world's experts on this stuff saying the
stuff that moved her is not available on
the platforms we have access to
now next step out from vr is ar
augmented reality and there have been
some successes there
with immersive geo games as they're
called things like pokemon
go and one from a local company here in
rural virginia
covens from rain pro games which is
gotten quite popular you know play it on
your phone you walk around looking for
witches to kill
things of that sort right yes what are
your thoughts about
this kind of low fidelity phone based
immersive ar
geo game well i've always been a huge
fan of geocached storytelling
whether it be ar based or just you know
like silent we we supported a novel
years ago about where you would unlock
chapters based on
where you were physically in the united
states and each chapter that you
unlocked in that place was
exquisitely written to
the landscape architecture and context
of that
space whether it be like grand central
station or um
you know a particular kind of
you know beautiful mountain view in in
los angeles
so it was really i've always been a fan
of geolocated
work i am come originally from a
theater and dance background i went to
nyu tisch school the arts for theater
and i was always jealous of my film
friends who would
be able to have this you know kind of
the same amount of time we would put
into creating a piece of work a piece of
storytelling
mine would be over in a six-week run and
there was no real documentation of it
and it didn't live beyond that
whereas theirs would live off and you
know could live off into
perpetuity as um because it's a
different it's a way of capturing the
medium and capturing time
and they can also distribute it more
easily than something like myself i was
on tour for
six years with stomp as a performer and
i had to do a
thousand shows and i still couldn't get
nowhere near
the level of visibility that my film
cohorts at tisch got but
i did not ever want to lose
the power of liveness and the synergy of
liveness
and so i think when i came my first kind
of coming across trans media the thing
that attracted
me to it was the fact that you could be
both live and digital
you could have both reach and global
community as well as
the richness of of ethereal ephemeral
kind of real-time experiences and when i
was at 42 entertainment
we played with that well i got a chance
to learn from some of the best in the
business
around how you can have up to 10 million
people
playing inside of a fiction and then
have you know cut it down to like 300 or
a thousand
they got to go through a rich experience
um in real time
and yet still reconnect that through
video capture and so forth
back to the bigger community so i love
geocache work so i'm just going to
put that out there first and even i
remember back when i was at 42
entertainment years and years ago
i remember going hey can we start
bringing in augmented reality
into these designs um at the time they
were doing things for like
you know the dark knight and they would
have people showing up and getting
geocached
you know kind of pieces of information
and they would
end up having whole masses of people in
the streets painted up like the joker
playing inside of the art alternate
reality game that they would design
around this fiction
and i was like well let's start pulling
in some augmented reality
and this is like early ar on smartphones
where you would like stand in your
parking lot and like a comet would like
crush you
there's like these kinds of and i was
just so fascinated by it
um and they were like sorry the
technology is way too unstable
the technology is pretty shitty right
now and they said maybe
maybe in a little a couple of years and
so forth and now
then pokemon go hit and you know
obviously it
changed everybody's perspectives around
adoptability and how
this technology could utilize in this
way this might be an insert for later
um but i also wanted to say interactive
film
is you know a ten if not older medium
and then interactive film the some of
the interactive film that i've seen
is phenomenal but what gets brought to
market is banner snatch
and i'm not dissing band or snatch at
all but it is
such a simple version it's such a
brand just a a b branching narrative
like stop the flow
of the story stop the flow of the
cinematic fluidity and that doesn't have
to be that way
and we we need to evolve the kind of
mass adaptation of
set-top relationships to this technology
to get to what
the innovators have already discovered
in terms of best practices and craft
and i feel the same way is true so
interactive doc
still has not been able to bring its
best
foot forward to the masses same thing
with virtual reality
but i definitely think um with augmented
reality
we still even haven't brought our best
foot forward some of the augmented
reality that i've seen
is so beautiful and seamless but we have
been able to do it from entertainment
standpoint
and pokemon go obviously is an example
of that and kevin and ingress and so
forth
but like when i was at sundance not this
last january but
well this last january too but the
january before
in 2019 i got a chance to see
this piece that
you walk into a bedroom and you have
this oh i can't remember the name of it
right now oh
it had a youtube sensation on there i
forgot but you walk into a bedroom
everything is physically laid out like a
set you know
and then all of a sudden this um
this woman shows up in the room with you
and it wasn't i mean a bit ghost-like
but very
very much unpixelated and she was
in a conversation with you in this
bedroom and then there was elements of
live acting that came into the space as
well
but it was phenomenal it was it was
mind-blowing
to be able to be in this room and then
also that year we brought micah from
magic leap
which is like one of the first times
that micah which is the augment
the augmented reality artificial
intelligence for the magic elite
platform
showed up and i walked into her office
she was sitting behind a big oak desk
and i couldn't see the bottom of hersh
this is a hologram she
stands up comes around the oak desk to
meet me face to face she's my size she's
life-sized
she doesn't talk yet at this point she
may be talking now i don't know
but she points to um a picture
you know the famous french picture of
like the pipe it's
on the wall she points the picture and
she tells me to hold my hand out and
then she
picks the pipe off of a physical picture
it erases the pipe on the physical
picture brings the 3d object of the pipe
and hands it to me and i'm holding the
pipe in my hand like it
i'm what i'm i mean this stuff is
phenomenal
and uh another one this last year
um breathe by diego fosse
he was he basically had a breathing
apparatus around our
our la you know around our torso and
four of us were in the room
and he is through augmented reality
visualizing our breath and how
it intermingles with each other but then
he had an augmented reality tree come up
in the middle of it
we could see how our breath goes
directly into the tree circulates with
it and then he expanded expand until
you get to see kind of this relationship
to the globe of our own breathing
and then two weeks later he sends you
real-time data of how
your breath traveled over that two-week
period based on
systems of air circulation on the planet
i mean you know i'm just saying like the
ar pieces are
just gorgeous and but yeah they're not
it is trying to find that balance
between where the pokemon go
entertainment audience
can meet the best of the ways in which
these technologists and artists are
finding
incredible fidelity in the medium yeah i
pushed back a little bit but you know
you told me this beautiful story about
the breath of the trees and i go damn
i'd love to see that or the guy plucking
the pipe i don't know was that the
famous usha picture with the pipe that
might have been
but those are kind of stunts you know
there's no story there there's no
narrative
and that's what drives definitely
definitely i
so i was talking about the quality of
the technology and those for sure
but another piece that i didn't get to
say talk about yet was a piece
that also came that year and this was a
what was it called dial it was called
dial and this is one of the best ar
pieces that i have
seen in terms of story they had a set in
the middle of the installation
there was a small miniature house all
white
um that was sitting in the middle of
this table and they projection mapped
from on top
onto this so that there was real
projection mapping on to the so you you
know gave the contours of the house and
and gave a landscape of green grass and
so forth around the house
and then the projection mapping and the
ar and this was phone based they are not
headset based ar
but you you had about five of us holding
our these cell phones up to look at the
piece
the projection mapping you could see the
little characters
in the house through the projection
mapping and then they would come out of
the door
and be fully realized um figures
that had scenes it was a domestic
violence
piece with a car accident all these
things miniature scale
happened and it was so dynamic emotional
and fully realized as a a to z script
with beginning middle and end and then
even at some points
you could look under the table there was
a pond on the property and you could see
the fish swimming underneath the table
in the pond
so there was this incredible
relationship to story
you got a chance to experience and then
you could also
kind of reverse your your relationship
to the story
uh by going backwards around the table
and go to the
to the back story so not only did you
see the present into the future of the
story but you could also
start from the present and rewind to a
backstory of these characters
beautiful piece incredible story
when will that be out to the market it
won't if that's the thing like these
things don't get seen
in a marketplace and you know i know
that they tried the arcade model but the
i went to those arcades they were shitty
content in those arcades they were just
shoot-em-ups
they they were not anything that had any
real kind of
um not even shoot-em-up story it wasn't
even like world war craft or
you know i mean it didn't even have that
much story it was just literally shoot
em up
shoot the zombies or something right it
was like laser tag experiences it wasn't
it wasn't cinema or or um real game
storytelling now here's an interesting
one that i have
stumbled across it really is not very
technologically deep at all but it's
deep in story
and it is an installation and it is
making millions and billions of dollars
for the backers and it's a
art installation called meow woods in
santa fe new mexico have you ever heard
of that
oh yeah definitely we've been in many
conversations with meow wolf and
they have one of my old staff friends at
sundance is married to one of the
originators
of meow wolf so yeah definitely aware
and
they they have made immersive
installation
i mean it's very i mean immersive
installation and immersive theater
um and the work that they're they i
think that they came
up at a time that was building off of a
lot of
pre-existing work in terms of i mean not
take anything away from them
and they also had our martin backing
them up so they were able to bring
um a full you know it was a risky
investment by him but definitely
one that i think paid off obviously
but yeah they brought in the best
elements of alternate reality gaming of
immersive theater like sleep no more and
all of the stuff that
came out of punchdrunk um as
to you know and there's some so it's
definitely
something we talk a lot about in terms
of immersive insulation immersive
experience
um immersive design yeah maybe a
business model i mean it's
so astounding i've been to it twice i
get out of santa fe from time to time
for my work at the santa fe institute
and their business model is pretty
simple they charge you 20 bucks to go
wander around for as long as you want
right and could you use some of these
holographic
or ar type platforms to build something
so outrageous that hundreds of thousands
of people per year
would pay twenty dollars to go wander
around in it for an hour
or two that that already
has happened if you go to you know the
17 million
i think i can't remember the exact
amount but um if you look at the
the mixed reality star wars thing at
disney
downtown
it's it's it's uh it's there it's not
you can explore they've got a little bit
of the ar
e g kind of you know assets of it they
got the shoot them up aspects they got
the
kind of have you have you been through
that experience no i have not
yeah it's it's they've and that's yes
there's definitely those experience and
then the uk i would say
is doing like marshmallow laser feast
they are
one incredible immersive xr
group that is making money in the uk
currently
also there's some places in france that
the model's working so
when they we're calling it the death of
vr like the death zone of vr
they were like shocked it was a couple
years back they were like
really the death of vr they're like
we're making more money than ever
right now in the uk so i'm shocked that
here in the states it's not
working so it's interesting to see how
these are but yeah i know it's
that meow wolf is i love it but they're
that's not new and it's also not
there's so many models of incredible
work like hero
is one of the pieces similar to that um
it's a piece by ink stories
out in new york city they created this
incredible installation where you got to
experience being a white helmet
um and and it's not it's all it's
it's mixed reality and that you're in
syria you know on like seeing the whole
situation a dog coming up to you the
whole thing then you're the
the building you're in gets um barrel
bombed
and then they have a whole installation
where you are actually physically
touching concrete and
and wrought iron and all these things
and you have to take the role the white
helmet to rescue
a little girl and even to the point
where you're touching everything
everything is still in virtual you still
look like you're in syria
but everything you're physically
touching is and then at the very end of
it
you actually lift up a concrete wrought
iron
thing in the and it's mapped exactly to
your virtual reality experience
and you reach in and an actor little
girl actor holds your hand
wow yeah i mean i'm saying like this
hyper reality
like you have no idea how incredibly
advanced the hyper reality is in this
sector and nobody sees it i'd love to
see that how much that cost
20 bucks well the thing is they haven't
found a place to
to take on the installation of it ah
it's too bad and to
show it yeah very interesting it's
interesting here at the cutting edge
so you talked about it on some of your
podcasts where you appeared
is that to your mind the modern artist
has to also kind of be an entrepreneur
to figure these things out
right yeah for sure i mean i think it's
i
i think it's a blessing and a curse it
depends like
those that can be very entrepreneur i i
studied i went and got my master's in
business
as well as my bfa so i have both
um and a lot of artists are
instinctually
like when i went and got my master's in
business i was shocked i was very
intimidated going into it i was like oh
my god here's this little like artsy
girl trying to go get a business degree
and i went in there um and i was mostly
with engineers
um and people that were you know kind of
business oriented but a lot of engineers
at this particular school and um
and i was like oh this is exactly what
artists already do
like artists that are hustling to try to
get their work
seen and supported and to make a living
the like it was just a translation issue
like much of it was just me learning the
language of
the business world to kind of do do the
kind of loss in translation
and then i brought that back um teaching
entrepreneurship to artists through
fractured atlas through the savannah
school of art and design
and other forms and it was really
interesting some of my artists
when i would take them through the
process of creating a standard business
plan would go from making no money on
their art
to being independent within a year just
because they were able to
you know were encouraged to create a
business plan and i felt
i graduated with my bfa without even
having had a class
around how to get an agent as an actress
like
literally no business education no
industry education whatsoever
coming out of a top world class that's
changed
since i mean the side came out in 99 but
that that's pretty unfortunate anyway so
i say that to say
that i do believe in the power of
entrepreneurship i think artists are
natural entrepreneurs
in many different ways there is a need
to either
be an entrepreneur yourself or to have a
close partner
that is going to be a partner you know
going to be a business partner with you
they actually have a term for it in the
visual arts world called the artist's
wife
which is interesting i like it
a little sexist there but what the hell
oh hugely
usually sexist but yeah just from the
statistics they showed that
most of the artists that had made it had
a partner that was very close to them
that was their business
uh manager but but anyway i saw that say
because you can't do everything not even
if they are business savvy
you just can't do everything on your own
and you need to get the right
collaborators and partners around you as
you're building your business
but sorry go ahead to your point i don't
i think i went a little off
no it's actually actually good you know
it's funny you mentioned in passing the
savannah
school of art and design my daughter is
a graduate of scad
really yeah they have you know one of
their mottos is we do not
educate starving artists right
you know they take some rudiments of
business they have a portfolio
class in the senior year and they
convince them that
you can't eat by art alone most likely
right unless you're picasso or something
and even he starved for quite a while
and so it is important but it is also i
do want to say that also i think there's
i do have to say that i've seen a bit of
a challenge in
a mark only market-based art economy
versus economies that do support artists
in different ways
in terms of what the artist has to
produce
and i think it's i mean you definitely
don't want to be navel gazing and
you know kind of creating masturbatory
work that nobody beyond yourself is
going to appreciate for sure
but i also think that some of the
compromises that artists make in a
purely market-based art economy
limits the full scope of what we may
need as a society in terms of reflection
and engagement and i think that some of
the especially in emerging technology
even not even just from the artistic
side but just the
technological innovations that connect
with art
or that artist that those that have
found this really beautiful
connection between art and technology a
lot of them are in europe
where they have a different model for
supporting artists until
something takes off and i think that
that i saw artists in this country have
to make certain compromises on that in
terms of quality
um and in terms of the depth of their
work
that could have and i'll give you a more
concrete example
one of the people that i interviewed for
this research project i did on
with the ford foundation was a marine
fan
this is oh stamford
you know grad went to you know worked at
pixar worked at
zynga where farmville and all these
casual games
had super success she is like amazing
for
the resume of silicon valley
and she was the only woman to get any
significant investment in virtual
reality during
the hype cycle in like 2016-2015 and it
was interesting talking to her because
when she was at
zynga she talked a lot about how
it was really hard for her she really
wanted to increase the kind of story
elements of some of the
work that was coming out and they were
kind of very resistant they just wanted
kind of using the addictive design model
of let's give them quick rewards
keep people you know going after those
quick rewards and we know now that those
have
major mental health issues with those
addictive design processes like
a lot of casual games use and it also
obviously is a cash cow because you're
getting people addicted to these
small endorphin that design in the boost
of these endorphins
and she was trying to argue for can we
build a little bit more story a little
bit more character
and got a lot of resistance finally she
brought in all this
statistics and metrics and laid it all
out and really really fought to get a
little bit more leverage
and she was able to get i don't know if
it was a regional or geo-specific
kind of area but she got a test area to
to test
this theory around story and around more
you know kind of in-depth
relationship with this stuff she did it
and what they found out
where they were resistant because it it
was it was a loss in terms of short-term
income because you didn't have this
addictive design kind of super fast
you know let me buy another packet of
gold kind of thing
but what she found what they found long
term is that they had much more loyalty
and actually made a higher profit
from deeper and you know kind of more
engaging story and character
so this is one of those tensions that i
think the market
sometimes has a bit of a myopic you know
kind of look
at and they they're not willing to take
that risk of let's try something a
little bit more
you know advanced in terms of artistry
or whatever because it's going to be a
market fail
when in reality if you give it the time
an investment actually
is healthier mentally and becomes more
engaging in terms of
and more profitable ultimately i think
that's where there's a little bit of
tension between
i definitely think artists are
entrepreneurs but i also think we have
some marketplace issues that
can produce sometimes the wrong outcomes
yeah it's unfortunately a trend
throughout our society that when we hook
absolutely everything to the tight cycle
of short term money on money return
we basically grind everything into crap
you said it much more eloquently than me
a little bit of an overstatement but
there's a hell of a lot of truth to it
make a good point that we need to be
conscious
of our social design and it would be
great to have more room
for socially supported art and as you
say some other countries do a hell of a
lot better job of it than the united
states does
and it really does not mean less money
ultimately i think it actually means
more money it's just more patient
capital you know
exactly now the art of storytelling here
in this
sort of post-modernist age we live in
right
post-modernism rejects broad powerful
narrative at least
yeah it's academic sense it does
but in the history of storytelling
archetypes have always been important
you know the joseph campbell etc
what do you think about archetypes and
storytelling in the modern post-modern
age
wow really interesting that you're
bringing that up um
so okay i have this i wrote a paper
about this in
undergrad around post-modernism and this
might
i i don't know if i'll be able to
articulate it as fluidly as i would have
back then but
um i was at nyu studying experimental
theater
very postmodernistic theater i was
studying
um theater critique so we had to go deep
into
kind of all the ways in which the
evolution of here the history of theater
and obviously this relates to all kinds
of
movements surrealism and dadaism and i
mean all the kind of
movements that are kind of uh both
artistic movements
as well as ideological or philosophical
movements and um
of course we studied post-modernism and
while i was studying these things i was
also taking
a lot of cultural anthropology courses
as well as
the history of latin theater history of
african theater the history of
islamic theater the history of asian
theater so i was
deeply interested in trying to
understand
how the arts and storytelling show up
across
cultures and it was really really
interesting to think about
post-modernism in that context
because you know essentially
post-modernism is you know has this kind
of
doesn't really stupidly simplify it
everything is random there is no
central truth there is no um stable
truth right
which really makes sense for a time
where people's sense of reality is
getting disrupted left right and center
from not only science and technology but
a whole new ideological lens on cultural
interactions
and so we're where a postmodernist might
say there is no truth everything is
random
it was my ex because i was i'll give you
an example i was watching this one
anthropological
film where a group of european
anthropologists went
to a village in pacific islands
and they watched a ceremony that looked
kind of crazy violent but then when you
really understood the whole story behind
it it actually was a story and a
ritual of coming to peace and
tranquility and they were talking about
how basically there's there's this idea
of this dichotomous thinking that
if something is you know which a lot of
kind of uh epistemological
systems can be very binary it's either
black or white yes or no good or bad
wrong or right and when you come out of
a context where
you know especially coming out of
european imperialism where there was a
sense of
let's go you know kind of bring
god to the world to save the world or
let's bring civilization to the world to
civilize everybody
there's a sense of a noble kind of
approach and so then you get to these
places where something that looks
heathen and
quote unquote savage and you really get
to understand it from an anthropological
level you're like oh my god this is
actually quite beautiful and amazing
then it can my because this is all
happening 50s 60s
when there was a kind of an opening of
the aperture around these narratives
that that there's this one way is the
right way and we're going to bring
our civilization to others and i think
that's where
in my opinion a postmodern perspective
came as like oh
if my truth if my kind of traditional
arts and ideology you know is true and
this which looks completely 180
different
degrees true then everything that
nothing's true
and everything is random and i felt like
you know that's looking at you know the
earth from a perspective if
i'm in a sandy desert then that's my
truth and you're standing in an icy
mountain then that's your truth and
we're trying to verbally communicate oh
this is
this is earth and you're like no this is
earth no this is earth no this is earth
and then when you widen up and you see
it from space you're like oh
both of these things are earth and by
the way this desert might be flooded
plain and be completely water
on one part of the year and this icy
mountain might be a spring awakening in
another part of the year so nothing is
stable
doesn't mean that it's not true it just
means that it's dynamic and it's truth
yeah i like that actually there are some
useful things in post-modernism
particularly you know the critical
perspective on the flaws of modernism
but when you take naive post-modernism
and say that it's all random that's not
true either
right but change is real right change
happens
all the time so i like i like that
that's actually a very nice synthesis
thank you and i i say that to say that
when it comes to
story and narrative um there's a real
movement right now among
narrative change and kind of social
justice workers where
the framing is you know each star in the
sky
is like a story but it's those who draw
the lines between the stars doing a
constellation or making a narrative
and um there's a lot of conversation
right now about how
who is drawing the lines between the
stars to
help us understand the relationship
between these stars
into this narrative right so i would say
that that is a strong
kind of element of story exploration
right now especially with
speculative fiction and speculative
historiographies
people are really trying to revisit
the stories that we've been told and
re-examine
all of the narratives that have kind of
like manifest destiny as being
re-examined as a narrative and
and so forth you know yep yep absolutely
and that makes sense i like that you
sort of preserve the perspective
of historical narrative forms but look
at it with a fresh eye
right well you
it's i think it's about being willing to
draw the star map completely differently
and
see oh there yeah you can draw a bull
there but you can also draw a crab
and you can also draw a panther with
those same stars
ah that's true too and nothing is wrong
they're all right and just trying to
understand
people's perspectives so that we're not
locked into
there's only one way to draw these stars
and that's as a bull
you know uh so when you talk about
archetypes
i'm i'm just i'm trying i know that went
a little bit far afield on that
but i i think that there's a kind of a
thin line between archetype and
stereotype
obviously as we all know and i think um
but there are kind of universal aspects
of the human condition and the
human experience that is a constant
refrain and is universal
and that's that i think that's critical
to storytelling and then there's ways in
which we complicate that
that i think is equally critical to
storytelling
i like it unfortunately we're getting
short on time here i got lots and lots
of other interesting
things to dig into but let's go to the
last
piece of my notes which is to tell us
about the guild of future architects
i like guilds i'm interested in them in
fact i was a co-founder of a makerspace
here in a little town
stanton virginia and me and my
co-founders organized it as a for-profit
initially but with no intent to make any
money
and we never did guess what but
[Laughter]
but then we converted it to a
not-for-profit once it got big enough to
stand on its own two feet
and we created a new set of bylaws and
called it the council of guilds
and it literally has a way to form
guilds in the areas of our
maker space we have fiber art we have
woodworking we have metal working we
have pottery we have
graphic arts we have robotics and each
one can establish a guild and then the
legal equivalent of the board of
directors is the council of guilds with
one representative from each guild it's
really quite interesting
wow that's phenomenal i would love to
talk to you more and learn from your
experience
yeah and one thing i do i'm happy to do
and then we can talk about it as i'll
give you a link
and we'll put it up on this episode page
for this episode to this document that
is our legal bylaws and which is even
more cool we got it through the virginia
state corporation commission which is
somewhat tight-ass and even better we
got it through the irs and got our
401 c 3 designation which is even harder
we're going 501c yeah 501 c3s we
we got ours in may and it was a
nail-biting
kind of rainy period you're just like
are we going to get it we negotiate that
so
that just gives a little background my
personal motivation why i am interested
in guild so
tell me about the guild of future
architects
yeah so the guild of future architects
has um
a mission to support future architects
as a guild um but basically sharon shang
who's the founder
is somebody who comes out of you know
madison avenue advertising
you know she was the chief creative
officer for huge media
um uh franchises like american idol so
you think you can dance all these things
and she kind of decided to step back
from that world
and go into deep um social
entrepreneurship and
basically impact and they call it impact
investing i don't know if she would use
those exact words
but she started experimenting with
capital and experimenting with
investment
for social good and had about 10 years
experience
in it and she kept noticing patterns of
success
around what she would identify as people
that are architects of the future and
architects of systems that become our
you know that that we end up end up
becoming our reality as we move into
that future
and she was really fascinated by her own
work
that had been able to architect systems
and futures she had architecture
background as well
formally educated in architecture and
was really curious about
that as a metaphor for people that are
designing future systems
not only through the lens of
equity and justice sustainability thrive
ability in terms of
you know economic viability but also in
terms of beauty
because she has a high heightened sense
of aesthetics and beauty
and when she thinks about beauty it's
not glamour it's not you know that
kind of beauty it's really the way i
understand it
is you're looking at if we're designing
systems that are not oppressive
systems that allow people to have what
they need to fulfill their potentials
then you start to see something that i
don't think we've seen on a global scale
ever in human history and that is
systems that unlock human potential
on all kinds of levels and that is the
beauty piece of it
when you see people in there being able
to fulfill their potential it
contributes
into a shared prosperity both
economically and
in terms of artistically in terms of
emotionally in terms of community
and so the guild of future architects
are people that are coming from a
diverse array
of kind of disciplines and fields of
knowledge
but they all agree on wanting to design
at a systems level things that are both
just equitable and prosperous
but also unlock human potential cool
how does one become a member of the
guild well we are just
still it's been very curatorial to this
point because we're a year in we have
145 members
um and we've been really hand picking
everybody based on
them having a strong practice of
collaboration co-creation
and that they have a strong expertise in
their field and that they are
um really generous in their their
because this is a learning organization
and so that's been our first kind of
criteria
and now that we're at 145 um everybody's
like the government the complete
governance is all every everyone on the
board is a member
the staff are all members all of our
contractors are members so it's really a
self-designed self-organized
self-governed organization
um and so this will be the next phase as
we open up
membership to application
how are we going to make sure that we
grow at the speed of trust
instead of just kind of growing just
based on who can
bring in cachet or money or those kinds
of things
that we really do hold trust um as a
high value
so how do we bring people in that are
you know collaborative and
bring as much to the group as they are a
regenerative relationship instead of an
extractive relationship basically
and so we'll see we'll see what the
membership committee decides to do for
when we open up applications but
if you're interested then you can
contact
hello at futurearchitects.com and we'll
have a conversation
cool you know back in the you know very
very important circle of trust you know
in the medieval period when the guilds
were amongst the most important aspects
of
you know the social operating system
they were quite rigorous on who they
would
allow to enter now some of it was
classic nepotism you know the easiest
way to become a member of the gold leaf
guild was to have your father be a
member of the gold league deal but there
were other ways in through
typically fairly onerous apprenticeships
four to seven years and then you had to
create a masterpiece and you know the
word masterpiece
actually had a specific meaning you made
a piece that was so impressive
that the guild would elect you in as a
master and that's what a masterpiece
was that's where that word comes from
we're definitely
exploring apprentice like right now i
would say the people that are in the
guild are
already a proven mastery in their fields
and in the work of collaboration but we
have been
deeply thinking about what does
apprenticeship look like especially
for the next generation of people that
are in college or just coming out of
college
and what does that look like what is it
what does the journey man look like
versus a master versus an apprentice
in in so that it's it's really a
defining
process and i would love further
conversation with you to talk about
how you would see journey versus
apprentice versus masterpiece and
something
that has these kind of intangible
elements to it like
systems design thinking yeah i'd love to
do it that would be fun you know in our
game b
movements non-political social change
movement which can be found at game b
group on facebook the idea of guilds is
something we talk quite a bit about
though i would say
we haven't put that much meat on the
bone so i could at least with
you at a high level
i loved it vice versa no it sounds like
you
and and i you know again i have to give
the credit to sharon for wanting to
adopt a guild-based
model rather than um another kind of
membership model
she she really feels that framing future
architects as a professional
class of people that people that the
institutions and communities and
individuals can turn to to help that our
bylaws say that the guild has to
dismantle within 100 years
or in 100 years exactly because looking
at this next hundred years
there's specific challenges that we have
globally in terms of climate change
um the adoption or the integration of
exponential technologies and scientific
breakthroughs
as well as kind of a a social
you know the things that we're seeing in
terms of kind of truth and
reconciliation around our kind of
social issues and now that we're
becoming smaller as a globe
and so she's like okay let's give it 100
years let's see
if we can get through this critical
period and then she said this
institution can become the compost of
the next institutions of that time
so my son is seven years old and i'm
thinking with anti-aging technology
and the scientific breakthroughs he
might be able to be around for that
closing ceremony that'd be cool that's
i love that that's a great idea in the
technical world we used to call
it ttl time to live in communications
protocols you'll often say okay this
signal has a ttl but if you don't get a
response in this time
throw it away that's interesting so last
topic
i'm unfortunately skipping over your
frameworks which are interesting but
that would be an
hour's conversation in themselves that's
so true
conversation for that and maybe we
should do that
which is on your website so a very
little brief coming
soon the collective wisdom platform
now that's ringing so bells for me tell
me what you guys are thinking there
oh my god i would love to know what
you're thinking of maybe you'll help
guide the design there no um so
about 2016 2017 uh kara murtaz
um who's on our board and uh executive
at the ford foundation
she had given a commission to both me
and to kat sizik another one of our
members for me
while i was working at the sundance
institute i looked at you know emerging
media and that was the making of reality
work that you'd referenced earlier kat
sizic
she had been working in participatory
collaborative co-creation
media for a long time through the
national film board of canada and beyond
and she started a co-creation studio at
mit
and she did a 280 page paper
it's called collective wisdom and she
uncovered this
deep and rich history of co-creation
as a mode of societies designing
themselves
and how under explored that has been in
terms of investment
and in terms of processes within kind of
the modern
um business or systems thinking uh ex
you know world and also in hers was
particularly through the media lens
where kind of loan authorship is often
more invested in than co-creation
processes
so that collective wisdom was an
inspiration for
the uh platform that we are designing we
have three programs we have our
community practice which is 145 members
today
we have a shared future program which
are collectives of members
that are working on specific design
designing specific systems
and future and working towards specific
future states and then the collective
wisdom platform
is where you know we can use the best of
in terms of media and technology
to coordinate future architects
uh within and beyond the guild we can
create
learning processes so that we are
whether anything
succeeds or fails there's always a
learning and we always feel like we're
going to succeed if we can capture that
learning and share it in an open source
way
and then the third piece is media and as
we're creating all these ideas about
possible futures
how are we creating storytelling that
can
illustrate that and spark ideas
about possibility and open up people's
minds to possibilities but also spark
dialogue around is this the future we
want and let's have a conversation
around that
and so some of the examples that are
coming out of it right now
we have a documentary series called the
radical imagination project
that's coming out of it we have a couple
of books that are emerging out of it
and we ran a 10-week sprint of futurist
writers rooms that were open to the
public
and out of that process we have 30
different narratives about speculative
histories that
surface design principles and
aspirational futures
and they're pretty freaking awesome so
we're going to be continuing to evolve
so it's a
media and tech kind of arm of the guild
i would say
yeah there's a lot of things that need
to be done there i mean
you know the money on money return
platforms like
facebook and twitter while there's some
good work that happens there
it's at least arguable at this point
that they're doing more harm than good
and you know thinking through what the
platforms look like that allow us to
collectively reason to have collective
intelligence and then
you know it's above my pay grade but to
eventually get to collective wisdom
strikes me as the kind of things we need
to do we're going to make it that
hundred years you talk about
i'm telling you it's so critical and we
have some
incredible people with better more
expertise than me
that have been looking deeply at this
work we have
people like sophia noble who wrote the
book algorithms of oppression
people like dr ruja benjamin from
princeton who wrote
race after technology in the new gym
code we have
eli pariser who created moveon.org and
upworthy.com
he is now working on a piece called
civic signals which is trying to
find ways of creating non-toxic digital
spaces based on
urban planning public parks uh theories
and
and uh practices so it's it's really
i mean locked dow who ran the national
field board of canada as interactive
as well as was one of the digital top
executives for the whole country of
canada looking at digital strategies
i mean these people that have really
battled with
the tension between market returns
and healthy you know democratic
environments
and digital space so it's hopefully
we'll we'll get to some i mean
it's 100 years so hopefully maybe by the
end of it we'll figure some things out
i know tv and other forms that were
emerging 100 years ago or still like
film and so forth
are still trying to work out their
ethics but we'll see what we can do
i think that's about all we can do is
try to do our best and what i like to
say is i'd like to
for us to be able to create a society
that we are happy to live in
and proud to lead to our children and
now for me
grandchildren oh congratulations again
i'm so thrilled that you are now
entering to this phase of your life jim
congratulations
well this has been a wonderful
conversation everything i would hope
to be and i got to tell you people go
look at that questionbridge.com website
that damn thing is
a thing of both great beauty and great
learning
thank you jim
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at modern space
music